# Dr. **Gráinne Costigan**

grainne@gcostigan.com gcostigan.com

Working in the most competitive and notable astronomy institutes in Europe, and the largest, current European space telescope, has given me strong team working skills, with a focus on attaining the end goal using innovative techniques and tools. I am looking forward to the next challenge of using my scientific knowledge and outreach and teaching experience to encourage the next generation of young scientist into STEM subjects.

## **EXPERIENCE**

# Research Associate

Leiden University & ESA's Gaia spacecraft April 2014 - Current

# PhD Student

ESO, Munich DIAS, Dublin Dec. 2009 - Nov. 2013

#### **Research Associate**

Dundee University, UK Oct. 2008 - Aug. 2009

#### City Astronomer

Dundee, Scotland Oct. 2008 - Aug. 2009

- · Member of data processing consortium of the European big data driven space observatory, Gaia.
- · Part of the team developing the data archive, analysis tools & validation of data.
- · Lead role in beta testing of archive, development of long term data and software preservation plan.
- · Designed and supervised multiple student projects.
- · Developed strong project development skills, from formulating the science question, assessing what tools are needed, completing necessary analysis to reach scientific goal, to final publication of results.
- · Developed independent work ethic with good communication skills through working with multiple supervisors in different locations.
- · Presented scientific results at multiple international conferences.
- · Implemented and developed computer vision algorithms for planetary rover navigation.
- · Lead the outreach program in the local public observatory.
- · Gave weekly public lectures, with night sky and planetarium tours.
- · Wrote a monthly astronomy column in local newspaper.
- · Held astronomy and art workshops for children in conjunction with local artists.

#### **EDUCATION** -

Graduated Queen's University Belfast (Northern Ireland), PhD in Star formation. PhD Dec. 2014 Title: Accretion Variability in Young Stellar Objects

Cambridge University (UK), Master of Mathematics. CASM Part III

Trinity College Dublin (Ireland), Theoretical Physics, BA(mod)

Masters 2007 – 2008

**Bachelors** 2003 – 2007

Science teaching in a primary school as part of a three week voluntary placement. Designed and implemented program for all classes from 7 to 12 years old. Full class outline (gcostigan.com/communication).

Co-Organiser of Interdisciplinary seminar on Medical Imaging and Astronomy. In connection with Erasumus Medical centre (Rotterdam)

Co-organiser of the 'Accretion and Outflows: Exchanging Mass, Momentum and Ideas' workshop at the European Space Agency.

#### **RECENT COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT -**

Sept. 2016 Bogotá, Colombia

Oct. 2015 Leiden, NL

Oct. 2015 ESA (ESTEC), Netherlands.

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**—

Python. MATLAB/Octave. MIDAS (FORTRAN based). ADQL (astronomical SQL). IDL. Bash. Latex. Unix.

twotonnetess.github.io